"Boosting Anticancer Immunity
with Forest Bathing"
Previously, I showed how exposure to
nature can have self-reported
psychological benefits, but
there was a dearth of data
on changes in objective measurements;
so, I was excited to see this paper
on the effects on levels of the
stress hormone cortisol in the saliva
of those partaking in
“forest bathing,” which just means
visiting a forest and
surrounding yourself by trees.
The level of cortisol in your
saliva is considered an indicator
of your stress level, and
after walking in a forest,
compared to walking in a city,
or even after just hanging out
in a forest compared to a city,
people’s salivary cortisol levels
were significantly lower. But wait
a second, the same effect was found
before they went to the forest. Huh?
Forest bathing was associated with
significantly lower salivary cortisol
both before and after, compared
with visiting an urban area.
Therefore, it appears that just the
thought of going to spend the day
in the forest relieved stress.
So, when comparing the effects of
forest bathing versus urban visiting,
the anticipation placebo effect
may play a more important role
in influencing stress levels
than the actual experience
of being in the forest.
So, I was ready to dismiss it
as just another nebulous psychological
effect until...I read this.
Studies on the effects of forest
bathing on the immune function
showed that visiting a forest
can induce a significant increase
in the number and activity
of natural killer cells,
one of the ways our
body fights off cancer.
That got my attention.
It all started with this study.
Twelve men were taken on a long
weekend to walk in some forests,
and almost all of the subjects
(11 out of 12) showed higher
natural killer cell activity after
the trip, and not just a little—
about a 50% increase
compared to before the trip.
Now, just exercise can
affect immune function,
but they weren’t walking any extra;
they were just walking
in a forest instead.
Yeah, but they also were
taken on a trip somewhere,
introducing other variables.
So, how about randomizing
them to go on
some city trip versus the forest trip.
And if there is some
special forest effect,
how long does the effect last?
Do you have to like walk
in the forest every day?
Before jumping into all that,
how about we first see
if it works in women too.
Same kind of set-up, and same
results: a significant boost
in natural killer cell activity
walking around in the woods.
And this time they went back a
week later to retest them,
and they were still up, though
after a month they came back down.
But hey, once a week should do it,
but it was a multiple-day trip.
Who has time to hang out in
forests all weekend, every weekend?
How about just a little day trip?
The title gives it all away.
Boom! Same thing! The same big jump
measured the day after the trip
compared to before and with
the same staying power.
Natural killer cell activity
still boosted a week later.
This suggests that if people
visit a suburban forest park
once a week on a day trip,
they may be able to maintain
the increased anti-cancer immunity.
OK, but I’m still not convinced.
How can you attribute the benefit
to the forest itself, when all
you have is before and after data?
To make the case that nature
had anything to do with it
you’d need a control group
that took the same kind of trip
but went to somewhere else instead.
And… here we go.
It turns out visiting a
forest, but not a city,
increases human natural killer activity.
Here’s the forest data just like before,
but nothing on a trip to
go walking in a city.
By the end of the forest trip,
the subjects experienced a boost of 80%
in NK activity after forest bathing,
compared to only a 10% bump
for the city walkers.
And both trips were matched for
physical activity, and alcohol,
and sleep—other things that
can affect immune function.
And so, here we go.
Confirmation of boosted immunity,
but only on the forest trip,
“indicating that forest bathing
does indeed enhance [natural
killer cell] activity.”
Moreover, they found that
the increased activity lasted
up to 30 days after the
trip. Check it out.
Still up a week later and
even a bit up a month later.
“This suggests that if people
visit a forest once a month,
they may be able to maintain increased
[natural killer cell] activity.”
OK, so, now that we know
that it’s a real effect,
the next question is, why?
What is it about forests
that gives us the boost?
And (you can imagine Big Pharma
thinking) can you make it into a pill?
We’ll find out next.